Guide to the Dick Thornburgh Papers, 1932- AIS.1998.30.09
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Campaign for Governor of Pennsylvania, 1978; IX.
  - News Releases, 2.
    - November, 1978 (Box 58, Folder 2)
      - Former Governor Scranton told rally that the truth was emerging about Flaherty's record as Mayor of Pittsburgh and would help carry Thornburgh to victory, Philadelphia, PA, November 1, 1978; 4.
      - New television commercial being aired around PA by Flaherty is branded as "false, hypocritical and desperate," Pittsburgh, PA, November 1, 1978; 5.
      - Described Flaherty's $7.43-a-person "fundraising dinner" as "one more example of phony imagery and blatant hypocrisy," Philadelphia, PA, November 1, 1978; 6.
      - Carpenters and Joiners Union Local 2274, representing 33 western PA counties, endorsed Thornburgh as "the only man who can bring jobs to PA," Pittsburgh, PA, November 1, 1978; 7.
      - Accepted endorsement of Hilary Czaplicki, community leader and Censor of the Polish National Alliance, Erie, PA, November 2, 1978; 8.
      - Renewed his pledge to hold town meetings on a regular basis in communities across PA, Erie, PA, November 2, 1978; 9.
      - District 33 of AFSCME, Hospital and Nursing Home Workers Union, International Longshoreman's Association endorsed Thornburgh as "the man who can bring jobs back to PA," Philadelphia, PA, November 2, 1978; 10.
      - The Philadelphia Tribune and The Pittsburgh Courier, the two largest newspapers in PA serving black readers, endorsed Thornburgh, Philadelphia, PA, November 2, 1978; 11.
      - Gubernatorial campaign continued to gain momentum today as dozens of endorsements by newspapers across PA were announced, Philadelphia, PA, November 2, 1978; 12.
      - Stressed the importance of the lieutenant governor's role in state government, Pittsburgh, PA, November 3, 1978; 13.
      - Visited a fourth-grade class at Hampden Elementary School in the Cumberland Valley School District, Mechanicsburg, PA, November 3, 1978; 14.
      - U.S. Senator Schweiker and Thornburgh pledged to join forces in the fight to see that PA gets fair share of federal dollars and job-creating projects, Philadelphia, PA, November 4, 1978; 15.
      - Quotes of Pittsburgh Mayor Richard Caliguiri, Democrat, Pittsburgh, PA, November 4, 1978; 16.
      - Robert B. Graham, Sr. and Robert D. Culp, sponsors of the Proposition 12 tax-cut amendment drive endorsed Thornburgh, Philadelphia, PA, November 4, 1978; 17.
      - Reverend Jesse Jackson, nationally known civil rights leader and director of Operation PUSH, endorsed Thornburgh, Philadelphia, PA, November 4, 1978; 18.
      - Two more major newspapers, The Erie Times News and The Johnstown Tribune-Democrat, endorsed Thornburgh, bringing to 42 the newspapers that have announced support for the Republican candidate, Philadelphia, PA, November 5, 1978; 19.
      - Accused Flaherty of soliciting more than $35,000 in campaign donations from persons who do business with the Allegheny County government controlled by his brother, Commission Chairman Jim Flaherty, Pittsburgh, PA, November 5, 1978; 20.
      - Former President Gerald R. Ford will make a campaign appearance with Thornburgh on November 6, November 6, 1978; 21.
      - Governor-elect Thornburgh strongly urged the General Assembly to approve a measure that would permit the convening of grand juries with multi-county jurisdiction to investigate organized crime and public corruption, Pittsburgh, PA, November 13, 1978; 22.
    - December, 1978-undated and unreleased (Box 58, Folder 3)
      - Governor-elect Thornburgh announced the formation of three transition study committees on Justice, Education, and Commerce, Harrisburg, PA, December 6, 1978; 1.
      - Governor-elect Thornburgh announced the formation of three more transition study committees on Labor and Industry, Energy and Environment, and Agriculture, Harrisburg, PA, December 14, 1978; 2.
      - Governor-elect Thornburgh announced the formation of three more transition study committees on Transportation, Personnel, and Budget Systems, Harrisburg, PA, December 19, 1978; 3.
      - Governor-elect Thornburgh announced the formation of the final three transition study committees on Health and Welfare, Administrative and General, and Community Affairs and Intergovernmental Relations, January 2, 1979; 4.
      - Governor-elect Thornburgh announced that he will nominate Penrose Hallowell, leading Bucks County farmer and conservationist, as Secretary of Agriculture, Harrisburg, PA, January 2, 1979; 5.
      - Governor-elect Thornburgh announced that he will appoint Robert C. Wilburn, President of Indiana University of Pennsylvania (IUP), as Secretary of Budget and Administration, Harrisburg, PA, January 2, 1979; 6.
      - Governor-elect Thornburgh announced that he will nominate Philadelphia City Councilwoman Ethel D. Allen as Secretary of Commonwealth, Harrisburg, PA, January 2, 1979; 7.
      - Governor-elect Thornburgh announced that he will nominate Lancaster Mayor Richard M. Scott as PA Adjutant General, Harrisburg, PA, January 3, 1979; 8.
      - Governor-elect Thornburgh announced that he will nominate former U.S. Congressman Edward G. Biester Jr. of Bucks County as Attorney General, Harrisburg, PA, January 3, 1979; 9.
      - Governor-elect Thornburgh announced that he will nominate a prominent Philadelphia-area educator, Dr. Robert G. Scanlon, as Secretary of Education, Harrisburg, PA, January 4, 1979; 10.
      - Governor-elect Thornburgh announced that he will nominate Helen B. O'Bannon, a member of the Public Utility Commission (PUC), as Secretary of the Department of Public Welfare, Harrisburg, PA, January 4, 1979; 11.
      - Governor-elect Thornburgh announced he will nominate Clifford L. Jones, who served in previous administrations as Secretary of Labor and Industry and Secretary of Commerce, to be Secretary of the Department of Environmental Resources, Harrisburg, PA, January 4, 1979; 12.
      - Statement regarding Gov. Shapp's last-minute appointment of Domenick Iannarelli to a five-year term as President Judge of the Philadelphia Traffic Court, Pittsburgh, PA, January 4, 1979; 13.
      - At January 15-16 celebration honoring the Inauguration of Governor Dick Thornburgh and Lt. Governor Bill Scranton, the arts of PA will be showcased, January 10, 1979; 14.
      - LeRoy Patrick, pastor at Bethesda United Presbyterian Church, said Flaherty "increased racial tensions in 1973 by advising citizens they did not have to obey PA Human Relations Commission order to desegregate schools", 1978; 15.
      - Marian Charles, past President of Women in the Urban Crisis and Board member of Pittsburgh Model Cities, said Flaherty "wouldn't get involved in planning neighborhood improvement", 1978; 16.
    - Unreleased, 1977-1978 (Box 58, Folder 4)
  - Endorsements, Responses and Articles, 3.
    The 1978 Campaign for Governor files include all major endorsements of Dick Thornburgh and William Scranton during the campaign, both Primary and General election periods. The endorsements are by newspapers, organizations or individuals and are alphabetically ordered. They represent a compelling perspective on Thornburgh's campaign and its targeted issues. A chronological index to the endorsements can be found at the end of the General Election endorsement lists, which well illustrates the increasing momentum preceding victory.
    The responses and articles are a chronological collection of files, including correspondence and questionnaires, sent to candidate Thornburgh by groups, associations, newspapers, or individuals, requesting his views. Some focus on a single issue, others on multiple issues a Governor would likely encounter. All inquiries were carefully researched by campaign staff and became the basis of benchmarks for goals and accomplishments during Thornburgh's eight years as Governor.
    Lastly, there are articles from the 1978 Campaign for Governor, in which Thornburgh's positions on issues are presented and published, usually at the request of the publication.
    The topics and dates for these materials are divided as follows: Endorsements, primary election: April 18, 1978 - May 12, 1978; Endorsements, general election: September 28, 1978 - November 6, 1978; Responses, primary election: January 21, 1978 - May 11, 1978; Responses, general election: June 19, 1978 - November 1, 1978; Articles, primary election: December 15, 1977 - April, 1978; and Articles, general election: September, 1978 - October 17, 1978.
    - Endorsements, Primary and General
      - Primary 1978 (Box 58, Folder 5)
      - General election, sorted in alphabetical order by title or last name, A-E, 1978 (Box 58, Folder 6)
      - General election, sorted in alphabetical order by title or last name, F-O, 1978 (Box 58, Folder 7)
      - General election, sorted in alphabetical order by title or last name, P-R, includes PSEA, 1978 (Box 58, Folder 8)
      - General election, sorted in alphabetical order by title or last name, P-R, includes PSEA, 1978 (Box 58, Folder 9)
      - General election, sorted in alphabetical order by title or last name, S-Z, 1978 (Box 58, Folder 10)
      - Democrat candidate for Governor, Peter Flaherty, endorsements, 1978 (Box 58, Folder 11)
      - Index of campaign endorsements, primary and general, 1978 (Box 58, Folder 12)
    - Responses, Primary and General
      - Gun control letter, 1978 (Box 58, Folder 13)
      - PSEA questionnaire, January 21, 1978 (Box 58, Folder 14)
      - Citizens Crime Commission of Philadelphia, February 23, 1978 (Box 58, Folder 15)
      - Common Cause of PA questionnaire, February 28, 1978 (Box 58, Folder 16)
      - PA Chapter of National Organization of the Reform of Marijuana Laws (NORMAL), March 13, 1978 (Box 58, Folder 17)
      - Walt Whitman Democratic Club in Philadelphia (gay rights), March 13, 1978 (Box 58, Folder 18)
      - The American Legion, regarding views on capital punishment, March 13, 1978 (Box 58, Folder 19)
      - United Press International Questionnaire, March 30, 1978 (Box 58, Folder 20)
      - League of Women Voters of PA, April 1978 (Box 58, Folder 21)
      - Philadelphia Journal Questionnaire, April 1, 1978 (Box 58, Folder 22)
      - West Penn AAA Motor Club, April 4, 1978 (Box 58, Folder 23)
      - People Concerned for the Unborn Child, Pittsburgh chapter, April 4, 1978 (Box 58, Folder 24)
      - PA Association of Housing and Redevelopment Agencies (PAHRA) questionnaire, April 5, 1978 (Box 58, Folder 25)
      - PA Social Services Union questionnaire, April 5, 1978 (Box 58, Folder 26)
      - People Concerned for the Unborn Child, April 6, 1978 (Box 58, Folder 27)
      - Homophiles of Penn State, April 6, 1978 (Box 58, Folder 28)
      - Pittsburgh Federation of Teachers questionnaire, April 10, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 1)
      - LAND questionnaire, April 12, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 2)
      - PA Pro-Life Federation, Pittsburgh, April 12, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 3)
      - PA Catholic Conference questionnaire, April 12, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 4)
      - PA Chamber of Commerce: "What Actions by the Government Would Be Most Helpful to Stimulate Jobs in PA", April 12, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 5)
      - Allentown Morning Call Candidate Survey, April 12, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 6)
      - Delaware Valley Citizens for Life, April 15, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 7)
      - Westinghouse Electric Corporation, April 18, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 8)
      - Common Cause questionnaire, April 21, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 9)
      - PA Coalition for Gay Rights, April 21, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 10)
      - Philadelphia County Podiatry Society (Medicaid system), April 21, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 11)
      - PA Chiropractic Society, April 21, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 12)
      - Retired Public Employees of PA questionnaire, April 21, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 13)
      - Hospital Association of PA, April 21, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 14)
      - Horsham Township Chamber of Commerce questionnaire, April 22, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 15)
      - Citizens Concerned for Human Life, Altoona, April 24, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 16)
      - Dauphin County Citizens' Alliance questionnaire regarding tax reform, April 24, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 17)
      - County Commissioner Nancy Shukaitis, Monroe, PA, regarding Tocks Island Project, April 25, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 18)
      - PA Young Republicans questionnaire, April 25, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 19)
      - PA International Trade Conference, April 28, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 20)
      - York County Farmers' Association questionnaire, April 28, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 21)
      - Clarence McKee, letter regarding the Liquor Control Board (LCB), April 28, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 22)
      - Bicycling Federation of PA questionnaire, April 29, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 23)
      - Philadelphia Inquirer questionnaire, April 29, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 24)
      - Philadelphia Bar Association, letter regarding merit selection for judges, May 1, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 25)
      - West Deer Township, May 3, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 26)
      - Mon Valley Progress Council, Inc., May 4, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 27)
      - Crawford County Senior Citizens Council, May 5, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 28)
      - PA Federation of Fraternal and Social Organizations regarding position on slot machine legislation, May 5, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 29)
      - WCAU questionnaire, May 6, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 30)
      - Senior Citizens Advisory Council, May 8, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 31)
      - Sierra Club questionnaire, May 10, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 32)
      - Western PA Public Health Council, May 10, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 33)
      - Homeowners Tax Relief Association of PA, May 10, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 34)
      - Lackawanna-Luzerne Consumer Council, May 10, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 35)
      - U.E. Political Action Committee, 506, Erie, May 10, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 36)
      - PA Environmental Council, May 11, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 37)
      - Miscellaneous responses, primary, March 29, 1978-May 1, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 38)
      - Governor Milton Shapp, letter regarding raiding lottery fund and Thornburgh's response, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 39)
      - American Association of University Professors (AAUP), 1978 (Box 59, Folder 40)
      - Gun control letter, undated (Box 59, Folder 41)
      - PA Farmers' Association questionnaire, June 19, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 42)
      - "Dear Friend" letter expressing concern over ceiling Shapp placed on Medicaid costs in PA hospitals, June 20, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 43)
      - National Association of Social Workers, June 29, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 44)
      - Veterans Political Action Council questionnaire, June 30, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 45)
      - PA AAA Federation questionnaire, July 6, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 46)
      - Midtown Square Action Council, regarding Thornburgh's plans to live in Governor's Mansion, July 13, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 47)
      - PA Council on Aging, July 22, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 48)
      - National Federation of Independent Business questionnaire, July 23, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 49)
      - American Institute of Planners questionnaire, July 29, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 50)
      - Tri-County Flood Recovery Coordinating Committee regarding Act 51, August 1, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 51)
      - PA AFL-CIO, "Right to Work" laws, August 2, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 52)
      - The Tribune-Democrat, Johnstown, August 2, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 53)
      - Robert Graham/Robert Culp, letter, August 7, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 54)
      - J. W. deGroot, Jr., regarding gun control position, August 11, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 55)
      - Metropolitan Citizens Organization of Allegheny County, regarding liquor license and organized crime, August 12, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 56)
      - Mon Valley United Health Services, August 15, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 57)
      - Berks County Mental Health Association, August 18, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 58)
      - PA Rural Electric questionnaire, August 19, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 59)
      - Americans United for Separation of Church and State, August 21, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 60)
      - PA Alliance of Drug and Alcohol Organizations, August 21, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 61)
      - Citizens for Animals regarding dog law and dog law enforcement, August 21, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 62)
      - Politically Responsible Nurses questionnaire, August 28, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 63)
      - Common Cause of PA questionnaire, August 29, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 64)
      - PA Association of Area Agency on Aging, September 5, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 65)
      - Matthew Moore, Pittsburgh, PA, letter regarding Landlord-tenants bill, September 6, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 66)
      - Margaret A. Ellis, letter regarding Equal Rights Amendment (ERA) and women's issues, September 7, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 67)
      - Thomas E. Colgan regarding corrections, September 8, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 68)
      - CALL-CHRONICLE NEWSPAPERS, views on state's highway problems, September 11, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 69)
      - The Editor, Pittsburgh Press, September 12, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 70)
      - Local 234, Transport Workers Union, regarding Department of Labor appointees and mass transit workers' strike in Philadelphia, September 13, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 71)
      - PA Association for Gifted Education regarding education of mentally gifted children, September 13, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 72)
      - PA Chapter of Wildlife Society questionnaire, September 14, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 73)
      - National Association of Social Workers, September 15, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 74)
      - PA Restaurant Association questionnaire, September 15, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 75)
      - PA Association for Retarded Citizens questionnaire, September 15, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 76)
      - PA Coalition Against Rape questionnaire, September 18, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 77)
      - The Evening Sentinel issue survey, September 18, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 78)
      - PA Society of Architects, September 18, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 79)
      - Lancaster County Restaurant Association, Marlin Thomas, president, September 22, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 80)
      - PA Forestry Association, September 22, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 81)
      - The Philadelphia Inquirer, regarding tourism, September 24, 1978 (Box 60, Folder 1)
      - Board of County Commissioners, New Castle regarding highway and bridge problems and Beaver Valley Expressway missing sections, September 25, 1978 (Box 60, Folder 2)
      - Western PA Surface Coal Mine Operators Association regarding law and order in strike situations, September 25, 1978 (Box 60, Folder 3)
      - Mid-Monongahela Valley Council of Governments, September 25, 1978 (Box 60, Folder 4)
      - Americans for Democratic Action questionnaire, September 25, 1978 (Box 60, Folder 5)
      - PA Newspaper Publishers' Association (PNPA), September 28, 1978 (Box 60, Folder 6)
      - Pittsburgh Press questionnaire, September 29, 1978 (Box 60, Folder 7)
      - PA Social Services Union (PSSU) regarding public employees' right to strike, October 3, 1978 (Box 60, Folder 8)
      - The Times-Sun, West Newton, October 4, 1978 (Box 60, Folder 9)
      - PA Science Teachers Association, October 5, 1978 (Box 60, Folder 10)
      - State Board of Public Welfare, October 5, 1978 (Box 60, Folder 11)
      - PA Rehabilitation Association questionnaire, October 5, 1978 (Box 60, Folder 12)
      - PA Society of Land Surveyors, October 5, 1978 (Box 60, Folder 13)
      - PA Catholic Conference, questionnaire, October 12, 1978 (Box 60, Folder 14)
      - Dr. C. F. Kay, Bryn Mawr, letter regarding abortion, October 12, 1978 (Box 60, Folder 15)
      - Bucks County Pro Life, October 12, 1978 (Box 60, Folder 16)
      - Phil Carter, letter regarding issues of concern to blacks, October 17, 1978 (Box 60, Folder 17)
      - United Steelworkers of America, District 15 regarding jobs, economy and barrier free design for the handicapped, October 17, 1978 (Box 60, Folder 18)
      - Mr. and Mrs. James Mizner, letter regarding practice of licensing nurses in PA, October 17, 1978 (Box 60, Folder 19)
      - Members of SOS and Concerned Citizens concerning Warrendale as potential site for facility for criminally insane, October 23, 1978 (Box 60, Folder 20)
      - Hertzfeld Associates, Inc. regarding diabetes, October 23, 1978 (Box 60, Folder 21)
      - The Democrat, Barbara Reese, questionnaire, October 24, 1978 (Box 60, Folder 22)
      - PA Association of Child Care Administrators questionnaire, October 25, 1978 (Box 60, Folder 23)
      - PA Commission for Women, October 26, 1978 (Box 60, Folder 24)
      - Juvenile Justice Center questionnaire, October 26, 1978 (Box 60, Folder 25)
      - Associated Press essay by Jim Burns regarding what Pennsylvanians expect from their next governor, and Thornburgh's ability to meet those expectations, October 27, 1978 (Box 60, Folder 26)
      - The Sentinel questionnaire, Carlisle, PA, October 27, 1978 (Box 60, Folder 27)
      - Thomas R. Terry, chief juvenile probation officer regarding problems of juvenile justice, November 1, 1978 (Box 60, Folder 28)
      - Alphabetical INDEX by person or organization of all campaign responses (primary and general), January 21, 1978-November 1, 1978 (Box 60, Folder 29)
      - Researcher responses, 1978 (Box 60, Folder 30)
      - Responses requested but unanswered, 1978 (Box 60, Folder 31)
      - PA Public Health Association (unanswered), 1978 (Box 60, Folder 32)
    - Articles, Primary and General
      - "Interview - Richard Thornburgh," Weekly Bulletin, Dillsburg, PA, December 15, 1977 (Box 60, Folder 33)
      - "A New Agenda for Leadership," Apparel News, February, 1978 (Box 60, Folder 34)
      - "What Makes Dick Run?" The Smaller Manufacturer, March, 1978 (Box 60, Folder 35-36)
      - PA Fireman Magazine, article based on remarks by Thornburgh, April, 1978 (Box 60, Folder 37-38)
      - "A Conversation with Dick Thornburgh," Dear Pennsylvanian Letter, April, 1978 (Box 60, Folder 39)
      - "Questions and Answers from Dick Thornburgh", April, 1978 (Box 60, Folder 40-41)
      - "Questions and Answers from Dick Thornburgh," conversations with Thornburgh by Rick Stafford, April, 1978 (Box 60, Folder 42)
      - "Questions and Answers from Dick Thornburgh:" Thornburgh responses and likely responses by campaign opponents, April, 1978 (Box 60, Folder 43)
      - Key Notes, regarding credit unions, September, 1978 (Box 60, Folder 44)
      - Apparel News, October, 1978 issue, regarding the economy and a climate for jobs, September 25, 1978 (Box 60, Folder 45)
      - Trunk Line, October, 1978 issue, "A Republican Newsletter," "Philadelphia Schools and PA Government", September 25, 1978 (Box 60, Folder 46)
      - Evening and Sunday Bulletin, four articles, "Why I Can Lead," "The Corruption Issue," "PA's Growth Prospects," and "Taxation and Finance", October 9, 1978 (Box 60, Folder 47)
      - TEANTEAY, Publication of Traffic and Transportation Association of Pittsburgh, November, 1978 issue, regarding roads, highways and bridges, October 17, 1978 (Box 60, Folder 48)
  - Campaign in Progress, 4.
    These files are in effect the essential working files of the campaign. They are divided into sections as follows: Organization, Volunteers, County Files, Scheduling, Media, Contributors, Correspondence, and Chron files.
    Many files are labeled either "Primary" or "General" referring to either the Primary election period-between Thornburgh's candidacy announcement and the Primary election (January-May, 1978) -or the General election period-from the Primary up to the General election (June-November, 1978).
    The Organization files refer to the organization of the campaign, and include for example: lists of staff, the many committees of Thornburgh supporters (Farmers for Thornburgh/Scranton, for example), and campaign petitions and legal opinions.